<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>LupLup</title>
<link>https://derharsh.github.io/LupLup/</link>
<atom:link href="https://derharsh.github.io/LupLup/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>My Personal Blog</description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.26</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 18:30:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Why QFT?</title>
  <dc:creator>Harsh Prajapati</dc:creator>
  <link>https://derharsh.github.io/LupLup/posts/why-qft/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<p>In my <a href="../../posts/first-post/index.html">previous post</a> I mentioned my interest in constructive QFT, gauge Theory and HoTT. To not sound like I’m just a penguin name-dropping advanced research area, I’ll try to describe how I to these fields and why I’m interested in them :3!</p>
<p>When I studied logic the first time I was really fascinated by predicate logic proofs OwO. In fact, I really enjoyed solving proof problems because it followed more logically than cookie-cutter “find the missing trick” problem. I had a fascination with abstract concepts from high school at age 15. This fascination always led me towards more abstract ideas and mathematics and along with my interest in physics I found that QFT as a formal framework is a bit shaky. Path integrals is not really a measure as it lacks sigma-algebra and renormalisation is just a trick which physicists use to sweep infinites under the rug and call it a day (again I hate tricks).</p>
<p>this led me to discover 80s work of Arthur-Jaffe on constructive quantum field theory which aims to formally justify the heuristics physicists use. And that is how I started reading more about this and I’m still learning more ^_^!</p>
<p>This problem is one of the hardest in mathematical physics and people are generally cautious of young students chasing the big problems just because of the glamour. However I believe that my reasoning for chasing this isn’t just glamour but it’s genuine philosophical motivation of rigour in theory. Physicists use QFT and make predict of scattering amplitudes extremely accurately however the tools they are using are a bit shaky and the lack of understanding of why it works is extremely important for QFT in curved space, and to avoid using the rules in wrong situations and get fake solutions.</p>
<p>Servus!!</p>




 ]]></description>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://derharsh.github.io/LupLup/posts/why-qft/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://derharsh.github.io/LupLup/posts/why-qft/image0.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hello!</title>
  <dc:creator>Harsh Prajapati</dc:creator>
  <link>https://derharsh.github.io/LupLup/posts/first-post/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<p>Today, i’m starting a blog page as a personal space to share my lecture notes, research ideas and codes (and some other random shyt). Currently im not enrolled in any institute tho but i plan to study bachelor in mathematics and theoretical physics soon. however ive been studyin a lot on my own using textbooks and lecture notes i was able to find online, so ill share my journey here :3</p>
<p>i only started talking notes in latex by the end of oct and for a while i wasnt consistent with it. but now ill try t be more consistent, hehe OwO</p>
<p>You can find my notes from the <strong><a href="../../library.html">Notes</a></strong> menu (obv), im writing the notes as i study so ull actuly be seeing them updating almost everyday.</p>
<p>As for my research interest, i’ve been reading a lot into constructive qft, gauge theory and hott (although i dont understand much “_“). i only have some surface level familiarity with the fields and very little technical mastery and although the problems in those fields are extremely difficult im highly motivated and excited to tackle them anyway (bcz im chaotic &gt;w&lt;). You can find more about my research in the <strong><a href="../..\research.">Research</a></strong> tab.</p>
<p>Lastly, im using quarto and github pages to host this blog, and giscus for comment system (you may need a github account to post comments). Codes can be found on my <a href="https://github.com/derharsh/LupLup">github repo</a>. currently there is no licence so u cant really use the code but ill make it open source using MIT or some other licence in future.</p>
<p>Tsch"uss!!</p>




 ]]></description>
  <category>General</category>
  <guid>https://derharsh.github.io/LupLup/posts/first-post/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://derharsh.github.io/LupLup/posts/first-post/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
