<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Harsh Prajapati</title>
<link>https://derharsh.github.io/LupLup/</link>
<atom:link href="https://derharsh.github.io/LupLup/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>My Personal Blog</description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.26</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 18:30:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Introduction to AQFT</title>
  <dc:creator>Harsh Prajapati</dc:creator>
  <link>https://derharsh.github.io/LupLup/posts/aqft/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<p>Continuing the discussion of QFT, i recently developed deeper interests into <strong><a href="https://ncatlab.org/nlab/show/AQFT">Algebraic Quantum Field Theory (AQFT)</a></strong>. It is a non-perturbative formalisation of QFT that axiomatizes the assignment of algebras of observables to patches of parameter space (spacetime, worldvolume). It’s roughly the “Heisenberg picture” of quantum mechanics used in introductory textbooks.</p>
<p>One of the main selling points of AQFT is <em>locality</em>, which is essentially a way to enforce that signals cannot travel faster than light, hence preventing <em>superluminal signaling</em>. This is why it is sometimes also called as “local quantum physics”.</p>
<p>Another plus point of AQFT is that some extensions of AQFT has provided several rigorous results concerning QFT in presence of a black hole, hence it’s one of the approaches to QFT in curved spacetime as well.</p>
<p>A modern formalism is perturbative AQFT, which sounds ridiculous because it’s completely opposite of the objective of AQFT, but the idea of pAQFT is that since traditional AQFT has failed to produce any rigorous interacting QFT model, we try to do perturbative approximations in order to reach non-perturbative solutions.</p>
<p>One of the key figures in pAQFT who wrote a book in 2017 is <strong><a href="https://rejzner.com/">Katarzyna Rejzner</a></strong>, I am still exploring her work and frankly it’s way beyond me.</p>
<p>A higher categorical formalism which is very similar but rooted in the Atiyah-Segal axioms, <strong><a href="https://ncatlab.org/nlab/show/functorial+field+theory">Functorial Quantum Field Theory (FQFT)</a></strong> axiomatizes the “Schrödinger picture”. Which is pretty cool but I don’t understand much.</p>
<p>One of the reasons why I though this could be the approach i want to take for non-perturbative QFT is because some times ago, i was thinking about using <strong><a href="https://pubs.aip.org/aip/adv/article/10/2/025106/1021638/A-short-introduction-to-the-Lindblad-master">Lindblading dynamics</a></strong> (operator algebra with a BRST-cohomology modified jump operator) instead of <em>Langevin dynamics</em> for Stochastic quantisation, essentially treating the noise as the environment. I know this idea sounds ridiculous and it probably is, because i thought it could avoid the gribov ambiguity (a huge problem in gauge theory), but this approach you’re not trying to fight the geometry anymore so the operator algebra will just “smooth out” the topological horizon.</p>
<p>It’s ridiculous because I soon realised that by trying to use Lindblad you lose <em>Lorentz invariance</em> (you could however use a fifth fictitious time dimension to handle this just like in stochastic quantisation but it’s messy), and make renormalisation more harder. so it’s not all good. But luckily AQFT sort of fixes those problems because that’s not an idea made by a procrastinating teenager.</p>
<p>Now, i don’t know if my idea of Lindbladian dynamics could work or not (it’s mostly just intuition honestly) but I thought geometry to algebra is a good change of direction. Essentially I sort of rediscovered AQFT so I want to explore more into it.</p>
<p>I’ll be posting more about AQFT in future posts. And i’ll probably explore my open quantum system ideas more, if we could provide a rigorous prove for 0+1D Matrix Mechanics it could be a nice fool tests for the theory but that could probably take a decade because of the sheer complexity of the problem. But right now I am sort of falling behind in entrance exam preparation, so I’ll be trying to catch up while putting this on some pause. I’ll just try to pass exams and not disappoint people who have high hopes from me.</p>
<p>Servus!!</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@flyd2069?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">FlyD</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/green-and-yellow-spiral-illustration-yQYQJaiypZE?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></p>
</blockquote>




 ]]></description>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://derharsh.github.io/LupLup/posts/aqft/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://derharsh.github.io/LupLup/posts/aqft/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Why QFT?</title>
  <dc:creator>Harsh Prajapati</dc:creator>
  <link>https://derharsh.github.io/LupLup/posts/why-qft/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<p>In my <a href="../../posts/first-post/index.html">previous post</a> I mentioned my interest in <a href="https://ncatlab.org/nlab/show/constructive+quantum+field+theory">constructive QFT</a>, gauge Theory and HoTT. I’ll try to explain why I’m interested in them!</p>
<p>When I studied logic the first time I was really fascinated by predicate logic and formal proofs. In fact, I really enjoyed solving proof problems because it followed more logically than cookie-cutter “find the missing trick” problem. I had a fascination with abstract concepts from high school at age 15.</p>
<p>This fascination always led me towards more abstract ideas and mathematics and along with my interest in physics. Through some chaotic explorations of Wikipedia and arXiv, I read that standard perturbative-QFT although makes predictions of scattering amplitudes extremely accurately, as a formal framework it is a bit “shaky”.</p>
<p>Path integrals are not well-defined measures, as it lacks rigorous <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Csigma">-algebra and has UV-divergences. Renormalisation isn’t rigorously well understood and through RG flows QFT is better treated as an effective field theory (Richard Feynman and Paul Dirac, the pioneers of QFT famously called it “<a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/how-renormalization-saved-particle-physics-20200917/">hocus pocus</a>”, that it’s just a trick which physicists use to sweep infinities under the rug and call it a day).</p>
<p>Understanding why the methods of QFT work is extremely important for QFT in curved space, and to avoid using the rules in wrong situations and get fake solutions, especially in non-perturbative regimes.</p>
<p>This led me to discover 70-80s work of Glimm-Jaffe on constructive quantum field theory which aimed to formally justify the heuristics physicists use. They were successful in proving a mass gap in Quantum Yang-Mills Theory in two and three dimensions but hit a wall in four dimensions, which is a Millennium prize problem and extremely difficult.</p>
<p>In the modern era, this problem is often approached from a stochastic perspective by using Langevin dynamics in SPDEs. Martin Hairer made a breakthrough with regularity structures for singular SPDEs, for this he won many awards including the Fields medal. However, the 4D Yang-Mills still remains an open problem because of how extremely difficult it is.</p>
<p>I’ll explained about QFT with more technical details <a href="../../research.html">here</a>.</p>
<p>The necessary background needed for this field (as far as im aware) is rigorous understanding of functional analysis, operator algebras, distribution theory, and measure theory. Currently my background is only basic understanding of analysis and algebra so I’m quite far from understanding the mathematics, but I’m making progress day by day at my pace.</p>
<p>This problem is one of the hardest in mathematical physics and people are generally cautious of young students chasing the big problems just because of the glamour. If I said that&nbsp;the glamour of solving big problems is not one of the reasons for chasing it, I’d probably be lying to myself. However I believe that my main reason for chasing it isn’t just for the fame or glamour, but a genuine philosophical motivation for rigour in theory.</p>
<p>So, this is why i want to explore more about this field and related fields such as axiomatic QFT, algebraic QFT and topological QFT, all attempting to make qft more mathematically rigorous. These are extremely sophisticated fields and typically people only work in a few in their lifetimes.</p>
<p>However, I haven’t decided to devote myself to this field right away, i’m in the early stage of developing my research interests so i think looking through them from a bird’s eye view would be helpful.</p>
<p>I’ll be talking about my other interests in future blog posts.</p>
<p>Servus!!</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@onkysf?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Yusuf Onuk</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/a-red-light-in-the-dark-yI6alVpYC6o?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></p>
</blockquote>




 ]]></description>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://derharsh.github.io/LupLup/posts/why-qft/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://derharsh.github.io/LupLup/posts/why-qft/image.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hello!</title>
  <dc:creator>Harsh Prajapati</dc:creator>
  <link>https://derharsh.github.io/LupLup/posts/first-post/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<p>Today, i’m starting a blog page as a personal space to share my lecture notes, research ideas and codes. Currently im not enrolled in any institute tho but i plan to study bachelor in mathematics and theoretical physics soon. however ive been studyin a lot on my own using textbooks and lecture notes i was able to find online, so ill share my journey here!</p>
<p>i only started talking notes in latex by the end of oct and for a while i wasnt consistent with it. but now ill try t be more consistent.</p>
<p>You can find my notes from the <strong><a href="../../study.html">Notes</a></strong> menu (obv), im writing the notes as i study so ull actuly be seeing them updating almost everyday.</p>
<p>As for my research interest, i’ve been reading a lot into constructive qft, gauge theory and hott (although i dont understand much). i only have some surface level familiarity with the fields and very little technical mastery and although the problems in those fields are extremely difficult im highly motivated and excited to tackle them anyway. You can find more about my research in the <strong><a href="../..\research.">Research</a></strong> tab.</p>
<p>Lastly, im using quarto and github pages to host this blog, and giscus for comment system (you may need a github account to post comments). Codes can be found on my <a href="https://github.com/derharsh/LupLup">github repo</a>. currently there is no licence so u cant really use the code but ill make it open source using MIT or some other licence in future.</p>
<p>Tschüss!!</p>
<p>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@francesco_ungaro?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Francesco Ungaro</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/a-room-with-graffiti-all-over-the-walls-Fd7JxSTpkCg?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></p>




 ]]></description>
  <category>General</category>
  <guid>https://derharsh.github.io/LupLup/posts/first-post/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://derharsh.github.io/LupLup/posts/first-post/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
